Scientists Collection 1563-1973 Mss.509.L56
American Philosophical Society
Scientists Collection
1563-1973
Mss.509.L56
American Philosophical Society
5.75 Linear feet 13 upright boxes, 8 oversize folders.
The Scientists Collection is comprised of individual letters and small groups of correspondence from American, British, French, and German scientists during the past three centuries. Although the content is highly varied, there is significant strength in astronomy, natural history, conchology, and geology. Among the scientists better represented in the collection are the astronomers William Radcliffe Birt, J.F.W. Herschel, and Franz Xaver von Zach; the conchologists A.D. Brown, Fred L. Button, Otto Mörch, Alfred Newton, Christian M. Poulsen, Temple Prime, Benjamin Lewis Vulliamy, and A. G. Wetherby; the physical scientists George Biddell Airy, Arnold Sommerfeld, Ferdinand R. Hassler, and Max Planck; the archaeologist Jean François Nadaillac; the philosopher William Whewell; and the naturalists Walter Henry Bates, Robert Chambers, Edme Dupuget, Robert Kaye Greville, Joseph Henry, John Stevens Henslow, John Lubbock, and Herbert Spencer.
Various
Naval History Note
The Scientists Collection contains at least one item which may be of interest to naval historians:
Gray, Asa. Letter to Charles Wilkes. 1848 September 27. Concerns payment for work on plants which will begin in November. Offers condolences on Wilkes bereavement. 2 pages.
Early American History Note
This manuscript collection falls outside the geographic scope of the Early American guide (British North America and the United States before 1840). It may be of interest to scholars interested in global history, international relations, imperialism, or the U.S. in the world.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Acquired variously, 1961-present.
Arrangement note
Each series is arranged chronologically.
Scope and Contents note
The Scientists Collection is a miscellaneous assemblage of individual letters and small groups of correspondence of American and European scientists from the 17th through 20th centuries. The disciplines represented are varied, with significant depth in natural history, conchology, geology, and astronomy, and there are separate series for physicists (58 items, relating especially to Max Planck, and a further 28 for Enrico Fermi), and American-Russian scientific exchange prior to the Russian Revolution (46 items).
Among the more extensive sets of correspondence in the collection is an interesting group of letters dealing with conchology during the 19th and early 20th centuries. Consisting primarily of correspondence addressed to the naturalist, Otto Mörch, the clockmaker Benjamin Vulliamy, or the bookseller, Herman Lynge, this correspondence includes letters from avid devotees of the science such as A.D. Brown, F. L. Button, Alfred Newton, Christian M. Poulsen, Temple Prime, A.H. Riise, and A. G. Wetherby, concerning the acquisition and exchange of specimens in Britain and on the European continent. Much of the correspondence of the Americans Spencer Fullerton Baird, William Stimpson, and Theodore Lyman is of a similar nature.
The circle of Darwin and, more generally, of mid-19th century British natural historians, is also well represented in the Scientists Collection. Included in the collection are valuable letters from John Edward Gray, William Whewell, John Lubbock, and John Stevens Henslow, and there is a small set of letters from Robert Chambers, as well as a fascinating exchange between the publisher John Murray and the naturalist, Henry W. Bates, concerning publication of Bates' The Naturalist on the River Amazon and other works. Several of the great geologists of the glory days of the science are also represented, most only by a few letters, including Adam Sedgwick, Roderick Impey Murchison, John Phillips, William Buckland, Gideon Mantell, and Henry T. De La Beche.
The physical sciences form a third key area of interest, stretching from the 18th century astronomer, Baron von Zach, through Ferdinand Hassler and George Biddell Airy, to the correspondence of a graduate student, H.M. Cave, completing his doctoral studies at Cambridge in 1929. Series III includes correspondence of Arnold Sommerfeld, Wilhelm Wien, and Max Planck. Series IV includes Enrico Fermi's letters to Enrico Perisco.
A small number of miscellaneous autographs and brief letters of non-scientists has found their way into in the collection, having been acquired along with scientific correspondence. A few letters, most notably of Alfred Russel Wallace, have been transferred to other miscellaneous collections.
Series I. Miscellaneous Scientific Correspondence 1563-1973 2.5 linear feet
Series II. American-Russian Scientific Correspondence 1789-1910 0.25 linear feet
Series III. Physicists' Correspondence 1786-1961 0.25 linear feet
Series IV. Enrico Fermi Correspondence 1918-1926 0.25 linear feet
Abbe, Cleveland, 1838-1916; Abeille, Louis Paul, 1719-1807; Adams, John Couch, 1819-1892; Agassiz, Alexander, 1835-1910; Agassiz, Louis, 1807-1873; Airy, George Biddell, Sir, 1801-1892; Akademiia Nauk S.S.S.R.; Amidei, Adolfo; Audubon, John James, 1785-1851; Bache, A.D., (Alexander Dallas), 1806-1867; Baird, Spencer Fullerton, 1823-1887; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815; Barton, Henry Askew, 1898-1983; Bates, Henry Walter, 1825-1892; Beadle, Elias R.; Beck, Lewis C. (Lewis Caleb), 1798-1853; Berzelius, Jons Jakob, Friherre, 1779-1848; Birt, William Radcliffe, 1804-1881; Bragg, William Henry, Sir, 1862-1942; Buckland, William, 1784-1856; Button, Fred L.; Carey, Mathew, 1760-1839; Cave, H. M.; Champollion, Jean François, 1790-1832; Churchman, John, 1753-1805; Clarke, Alexander Ross, 1828-1914; Clarke, Frieda; Clarke, Hans Thacher, 1887-1972; Compton, K. T., (Karl Taylor), 1887-1954; Cooper, Astley, Sir, 1768-1841; Cooper, Thomas, 1805-1892; Cope, E. D., (Edward Drinker), 1840-1897; Coxe, John Redman, 1773-1864; De La Beche, Henry T., (Henry Thomas), 1796-1855; Dunglison, Robley, 1798-1869; Dupuget, Edme Jean Antoine, comte, 1742-1801; Einstein, Albert, 1879-1955; Elie de Beaumont, L., (Leonce), 1798-1874; Fermi, Enrico, 1901-1954; Forster, Johann Reinhold, 1729-1798; Galton, Francis, Sir, 1822-1911; Gay-Lussac, Joseph Louis, 1878-1950; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888; Gray, John Edward, 1800-1875; Gray, Joseph Alexander, 1884-1966; Greville, Robert Kaye, 1794-1866; Harlan, Richard, 1796-1843; Hassler, F. R, (Ferdinand Rudolph), 1770-1843; Heckewelder, John Gottlieb Ernestus, 1743-1823; Henry, Joseph, 1797-1878; Henslow, J. S. (John Stevens), 1796-1861; Herschel, John F. W., Sir, (John Frederick William), 1792-1871; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859; Huxley, Thomas Henry, 1825-1895; Ingham, Samuel Delucenna, 1779-1860; Jackson, Abraham Valentine Wiliams, 1862-1937; Jenner, William, Sir, 1815-1898; Jones, William; Kirkbride, Thomas Story, 1809-1883; Krebs, Hans Adolf, Sir; Kuiper, Gerard Peter, 1905-; La Condamine, Charles-Marie de, 1701-1774; La Cépède, M. le comte de, (Bernard Germain Etienne de La Ville sur Illon), 1756-1825; Lardner, Dionysius, 1793-1859; Lubbock, John, Sir, 1834-1913; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875; Lyman, Theodore, 1833-1897; Lynge, Herman Henrik Julius, 1822-1897; Maury, Matthew Fontaine, 1806-1873; Michaux, Francois André, 1770-1855; Morton, Samuel George, 1799-1851; Murray, John, 1808-1892; Mörch, Otto Andreas Lowson, 1828-1878; Nadaillac, Jean François Albert du Pouget, marquis de, 1818-1904; Nadault de Buffon, Henri, 1831-1890; Perisco, Enrico; Phillips, John, 1800-1874; Planck, Max, 1858-1947; Playfair, John, 1748-1819; Poulsen, Christian Marinus, 1818-; Priestley, Joseph, 1733-1804; Prime, Temple, 1832-1903; Richards, Alfred N. (Alfred Newton), 1876-1966; Sedgwick, Adam, 1785-1873; Seeger, Raymond John, 1906-; Segrè, Emilio Gino, 1905-1989; Silliman, Benjamin, Jr., 1816-1885; Sommerfeld, Arnold, 1868-1951; Sowerby, George Brettingham, 1788-1854; Spalding, Lyman, 1772-1821; Spencer, Herbert, 1820-1903; Stillé, Alfred, 1813-1900; Stimpson, William, 1832-1872; Thouin, André, 1747-1824; Tyndall, John, 1820-1893; Vaughan, John, 1756-1841; Vulliamy, Benjamin Lewis, 1780-1854; Wetherby, A. G.; Whewell, William, 1794-1866; Wien, W., (Wilhelm), 1864-1928; Zach, Franz Xaver, Freiherr von, 1754-1832; Astronomy; Astronomy--Early works to 1800; Beyond Early America; Conchology; Evolution (Biology); Geology; Natural history; Paleontology; Photographs; Physicists.; Physics; Physics--Early works to 1800; Science; Shells.
- Series I. Correspondence, 1563-1973; 5.0 lin. feet 10 upright boxes, 8 oversize folders.
  Scope and Contents note
  Miscellaneous correspondence of American, British, French, and German scientists from the 17th through the 20th centuries.
  - Table of Contents, 509 L56
  - Table of Contents, 509 L56.f
  - Table of Contents, 509 L56.po
  - Statement, 1563 Feb.; Champi, Bartolomeo
    Immediate Source of Acquisition note
    1962-2244ms
  - Letter to Unidentified recipient, 1655 Apr. 23; Oesterreich, Leopold William
    A.L.S. 2 pp., folio. In Italian. Acknowledges receipt of box of pomegranates, requesting some other items for his work, and discussing theories of germination of plants.
    1975-738ms
  - Registration certificate of a company to enable boats to come up the Loire to Rouanne, 1702 Jun. 21; Oversize box
  - Letter to Bosgnet, Monsieur, 1747; LeGalloy
    1973-1750ms
  - Letter to Messieurs, 1760 Feb. 28; Schaeffer, Jacob Chrétien
    1970-3ms
  - Letter to Abeille, Louis Paul, 1719-1807, 1761 Sep. 7; Société Nationale d'Agriculture de France.
  - Letter to Abeille, Louis Paul, 1719-1807, 1761 Sep. 24; Menon de Turbilly, Louis François Henri, marquis de, 1717-1776
  - Letter to Unidentified recipient, 1764 Aug. 7; Morton, James Douglas, 15th Earl
    1975-737ms
  - Letter to Malesherbes, Chrétien Guillaume de Lamoignon de, 1721-1794, 1765 Sep. 12; La Condamine, Charles-Marie de, 1701-1774
  - Letter to Du Tours, 1766 Jul. 8; Alembert, Jean le Rond de, 1717-1783
    1967-2485ms
  - Letter to Du Tours, 1766 Sep. 11; Alembert, Jean le Rond de, 1717-1783
  - Letter to Unidentified recipient, 1767 May 15; Emerson, William, 1701-1782
  - Letter to Morgan, John, 1735-1789, 1767 Nov. 3; Photocopy.; Jamineau, Isaac
    Includes: An account of the eruption of Vesuvius
    1969-1287ms
  - Letter to Luc, J. A. (Jean André), 1727-1817, 1769 Apr. 26; La Condamine, Charles-Marie de, 1701-1774
    1962-2408ms
    In French. Includes typed copy.
  - Letter to Nourse(?), 1769 Oct. 7; Emerson, William, 1701-1782
  - Prescription, 1771 Mar. 1; Darwin, Erasmus, 1731-1802
    1976-1490ms
  - Letter to Unidentified recipient, 1778 Jul. 27; Fuss, Nikolai Ivanovich, 1755-1826
  - Letter to Unidentified recipient, 1782 Jan. 4; Bexon
  - Letter to Pritchard, Arthur, 1782 May 21; Jones, William
    1962-2273ms
  - Letter to Unidentified recipient, 1784 Apr. 6; Beckmann, Johann, 1739-1811
  - Letter to Cotte, L. (Louis), 1740-1815, 1784 Apr. 9; Swinden, Jan Hendrik van, 1746-1823
  - Letter to Blagden, Charles, 1748-1820, 1784 Dec. 5; Zach, Franz Xaver, Freiherr von, 1754-1832
    1962-1461ms
  - Letter to Blagden, Charles, 1748-1820, 1785 Jan. 24; Zach, Franz Xaver, Freiherr von, 1754-1832
  - Letter to Blagden, Charles, 1748-1820, 1785 Feb. 12; Zach, Franz Xaver, Freiherr von, 1754-1832
  - Letter to Unidentified recipient, 1785 Jun. 15; Thouin, André, 1747-1824
  - Letter to Gillet de Laumont, François Pierre Nicolas, 1747-1834, 1787 Jun. 12; Dupuget, Edme Jean Antoine, comte, 1742-1801
  - Letter to Unidentified recipient, 1788 Jun. 1; La Cépède, M. le comte de, (Bernard Germain Etienne de La Ville sur Illon), 1756-1825
  - Letter to Vulliamy, Benjamin Lewis, 1780-1854, 1789 Oct. 17; Phipps, Henry, 1st Earl of Mulgrave
  - Letter to Unidentified recipient, 1791 Jun. 6; Martyn, Thomas, 1735-1825
  - Letter to Unidentified recipient, 1791 Nov. 9; Bode, Johann Elert, 1747-1826
    1962-2276ms
  - Letter to Banks, Joseph, 1743-1820, 1791 Dec. 25; Latham, John, 1740-1837
    1975-301ms
  - Letter to Wingrave, Francis, 1793 Mar. 31; Maskelyne, Nevil, 1732-1811
  - Letter to Vaughan, John, 1755-1841, 1793 Aug. 22; Photocopy.; Priestley, Joseph, 1733-1804
  - Letter to Unidentified recipient, 1793 Nov. 25; Mitchill, Samuel L., (Samuel Latham), 1764-1831
    Photocopy of original in the College of Physicians
    1963-217ph
  - Letter to Heckewelder, John Gottlieb Ernestus, 1743-1823, 1794 Mar. 22; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
  - Letter to Gillet de Laumont, François Pierre Nicolas, 1747-1834, 1794 Nov. 2; Dupuget, Edme Jean Antoine, comte, 1742-1801
  - Letter to Gillet de Laumont, François Pierre Nicolas, 1747-1834, 1794 Dec. 5; Dupuget, Edme Jean Antoine, comte, 1742-1801
  - Letter to Heckewelder, John Gottlieb Ernestus, 1743-1823, 1795 Aug. 15; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
  - Letter to Heckewelder, John Gottlieb Ernestus, 1743-1823, 1795 Sep. 6; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
  - Letter to Heckewelder, John Gottlieb Ernestus, 1743-1823, 1795 Dec. 2; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
  - Letter to Heckewelder, John Gottlieb Ernestus, 1743-1823, 1795 Dec. 28; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
  - Letter to Heckewelder, John Gottlieb Ernestus, 1743-1823, 1796 Jan. 13; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
  - Letter to Heckewelder, John Gottlieb Ernestus, 1743-1823, 1796 Mar. 23; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
  - Letter to Heckewelder, John Gottlieb Ernestus, 1743-1823, 1796 May 17; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
  - Letter to Heckewelder, John Gottlieb Ernestus, 1743-1823, 1796 May 23; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
  - Letter to Heckewelder, John Gottlieb Ernestus, 1743-1823, 1796 Aug. 29; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
  - Letter to Heckewelder, John Gottlieb Ernestus, 1743-1823, 1796 Sep. 22; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
  - Letter to Heckewelder, John Gottlieb Ernestus, 1743-1823, 1796 Oct. 28; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
  - Letter to Gillet de Laumont, François Pierre Nicolas, 1747-1834, 1797 Jan. 16; Dupuget, Edme Jean Antoine, comte, 1742-1801
  - Letter to Heckewelder, John Gottlieb Ernestus, 1743-1823, 1797 Nov. 20; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
  - Letter to Heckewelder, John Gottlieb Ernestus, 1743-1823, 1798 Feb. 11; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
  - Letter to Heckewelder, John Gottlieb Ernestus, 1743-1823, 1798 Feb. 14; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
  - Letter to Heckewelder, John Gottlieb Ernestus, 1743-1823, 1798 May 18; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
  - Letter to Heckewelder, John Gottlieb Ernestus, 1743-1823, 1798 Dec. 4; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
  - Letter to Heckewelder, John Gottlieb Ernestus, 1743-1823, 1798 Dec. 18; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
  - Letter to Lee, William, 1800 Jan. 1; Pearson, George, 1751-1828
    1980-1963ms
  - Letter to Livingston, 1800 Mar. 13; Priestley, Joseph, 1733-1804
  - Letter to Heckewelder, John Gottlieb Ernestus, 1743-1823, 1800 Apr. 17; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
  - Letter to Unidentified recipient, 1800 Nov. 27; Zach, Franz Xaver, Freiherr von, 1754-1832
    1966-1281ms
  - Letter to Bouvard, Alexis, 1767-1843, 1801 Mar. 13; Laplace, Pierre Simon, marquis de, 1749-1827
  - Letter to Currie, William, 1754-1828, 1801 Sep. 30; Anderson, William
    1967-1221ms
    Azores--Description and travel
  - Letter to Coxe, John Redman, 1773-1864, 1802 Feb. 11; Vaughan, John, 1756-1841
  - Letter to Pickens, G., 1802 May 1; Michaux, Francois André, 1770-1855
    1967-2553ms
  - Letter to Baron, Lord Chief, 1802 Jun. 3; Russell, James, 1754-1836
  - Letter to Carey, Matthew, 1760-1839, 1802 Oct. 2; Priestley, Joseph, 1733-1804
  - Letter to Baker, Mr., 1803 May 20; Sowerby, James, 1757-1822
    1974-999f.ms
  - Letter to Coxe, John Redman, 1773-1864, 1804 Feb. 11; Spalding, Lyman, 1772-1821
  - Letter to Unidentified recipient, 1804 Apr. 21; La Cépède, M. le comte de, (Bernard Germain Etienne de La Ville sur Illon), 1756-1825
  - Letter to Wells, 1804 Sep. 7; Rafinesque, C. S., (Constantine Samuel ), 1783-1840
  - Letter to Unidentified recipient, 1804 Oct. 26; Bingley, William, 1774-1823
  - Letter to Coxe, John Redman, 1773-1864, 1804 Nov. 28; Spalding, Lyman, 1772-1821
  - Receipt of estate papers..., 1805 Jan. 26; Andree, John, fl.1790
  - Letter to Schuster, 1805 Feb. 8; Huggins, William, Sir, 1824-1910
  - Letter to Heckewelder, John Gottlieb Ernestus, 1743-1823, 1805 Mar. 14; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
  - Letter to Unidentified recipient, 1805 Jul. 25.; Zach, Franz Xaver, Freiherr von, 1754-1832
  - Letter to Vulliamy, Benjamin Lewis, 1780-1854, 1805 Oct. 4; Lennox, Charles, Duke of Richmond, 1701-1750
  - Letter to Unidentified recipient, 1805 Oct. 24; Gilbert, Davies, 1767-1839
  - Letter to Brickell, 1806 Jan. 23; Muhlenberg, Henry, 1753-1815
  - Letter to Cadell & Davies., 1806 Mar. 31; Playfair, John, 1748-1819
  - Letter to Unidentified recipient, 1806 Jul. 31; Deluc, Jean André
  - Letter to Wheatley, Henry B., 1807 Feb. 18; Ball, Robert S. (Robert Stawell), Sir, 1840-1913
    1977-603a.ms
  - Letter to Gilbert, Davies, 1767-1839, 1808 Apr. 7; Maskelyne, Nevil, 1732-1811
  - Letter to Vulliamy, Benjamin Lewis, 1780-1854, 1808 Aug. 5; Bath, Thynne, Marquis of
  - Letter to Silvestre, 1808 Dec. 15; Le Mans (France). Société Libre des Arts.
  - Letter to Unidentified recipient, 1809 Apr. 7; Reger, Max
  - Letter to Heckewelder, John Gottlieb Ernestus, 1743-1823, 1809 Jun. 8; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
  - Letter to Vulliamy, Benjamin Lewis, 1780-1854, 1809 Aug. 17; ?
  - Letter to Silvestre, 1809 Dec. 16; Le Mans (France). Société Libre des Arts.
  - Letter to Heckewelder, John Gottlieb Ernestus, 1743-1823, 1810 Jan. 7; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815
  - Letter to Peck, W. D., 1810 Jan. 10; Muhlenberg, Henry, 1753-1815
  - Letter to Vulliamy, Benjamin Lewis, 1780-1854, 1810 May 22; Campbell, Marquis of Breadalbane
  - Letter to Miller, Sarah, 1810 Dec. 22; Wilson, Alexander
  - Letter to Vulliamy, Mssrs., 1811 May 18; Dublin, Bishop of
  - Letter to Omer, 1811 Aug. 21; Muhlenberg, Henry, 1753-1815
  - Letter to Playfair, William, 1759-1823, 1811 Aug. 21; Playfair, John, 1748-1819
  - Letter to Vulliamy, Benjamin Lewis, 1780-1854, 1811 Sep. 15; Bangor, Bishop of
  - Letter to Chappe, 1811 Sep. 17; Société Nationale d'Agriculture de France.
  - Letter to Vulliamy, Benjamin Lewis, 1780-1854, 1811 Oct. 8; Bedford, Russell, Duchess of
  - Letter to Vulliamy, Benjamin Lewis, 1780-1854, 1811 Oct. 15; Fienne, Henry Pelham, 4th duke of Newcastle
  - Letter to Lackington, Allen & Co., 1812 May 19; Latham, John, 1740-1837
  - Letter Certificate for Surgery, 1812 Jul. 17; Hughes, Charles C.
  - Letter to Vulliamy, Benjamin Lewis, 1780-1854, 1812 Aug. 3; Clifford, Edward Southwell, Baron, 1767-1832
  - Letter to Peyré, Monsieur, 1812 Oct. 20; Ampère, André-Marie, 1775-1836
    1966-2039ms
  - Letter to Unidentified recipient, 1813 Apr. 16; Kendrick, Joseph
  - Letter to Vulliamy, Benjamin Lewis, 1780-1854, 1813 Jun. 10; Bristol, J.
  - Letter to Vulliamy, Benjamin Lewis, 1780-1854, 1813 Jun. 16; King, Peter King, Lord, 1776-1833
  - Letter to Peck, William, 1813 Dec. 16; Swartz, Olaf
  - Letter to Vulliamy, Mssrs., 1814 Mar. 27; Bantry, Lord
  - Letter to Nevins, John, 1814 Oct. 17; Allen, William
  - Letter to Woods, Joseph, 1814 Nov. 8; Howard, Luke
  - Letter to Vulliamy, Benjamin Lewis, 1780-1854, 1815 Feb. 26; Egerton, Francis Henry, Earl of Bridgewater, 1756-1829
  - Letter to La Rochefoucauld-Liancourt, François Alexandre Frederic, duc de, 1747-1827, 1815 Jan. 16; Arcet, Jean-Pierre-Joseph d', 1777-1844
  - Letter to Vulliamy, Benjamin Lewis, 1780-1854, 1815 Jun. 25; Yarborough, Lord
  - Letter to Vulliamy, Benjamin Lewis, 1780-1854, 1815 Sep. 10; Sunderland, Lord
  - Letter to Vulliamy, Benjamin Lewis, 1780-1854, 1815 Oct. 10; Salisbury, Bishop of
  - Letter to Vulliamy, Benjamin Lewis, 1780-1854, 1815 Oct. 23; Cooper, Shaftesbury, Earl of
  - Letter to Vulliamy, Benjamin Lewis, 1780-1854, 1816 Jan. 20; Whitworth, Charles Whitworth, Earl
  - Letter to Vulliamy, Benjamin Lewis, 1780-1854, 1816 Aug. 1; Mount-Edgcumbe, Edgcumbe, Richard, 2nd Earl of
  - Letter to Monro, George, 1816 Aug. 14.; Monro, S.
  - Letter to Dupont, 1816 Sep. 27; Cueron
  - Letter to Poulsen, Christian Marinus, 1818-, 1816 Nov. 29; H. Pontoppidan & Co.
    1965-2170ms
    Conchology
  - Letter to Anderson, Alexander, 1817 Mar.; Mitchill, Samuel L., (Samuel Latham), 1764-1831
  - Letter to Vulliamy, Benjamin Lewis, 1780-1854, 1817 Apr. 17; Churchill, Lord
  - Letter to Bartram, William, 1729-1823, 1817 Jun. 2; Wistar, Caspar, 1761-1818
  - Letter to AMsS Cy, Eulogium on Caspar Wistar., 1818 Jan. 17; James, T. C.
    Wistar, Caspar, 1761-1818
  - Letter to Vulliamy, Benjamin Lewis, 1780-1854, 1818 Feb. 25; Kaye, John, Bishop of Lincoln
  - Letter to Unidentified recipient, 1819 Jan.; Whitlow, Charles
  - Letter to Unidentified recipient, 1819 Apr. 21; Zach, Franz Xaver, Freiherr von, 1754-1832
  - Letter to Vulliamy & Sons, 1819 Aug. 7; Killaloe, Bishop of
  - Letter to Barker, Mr., 1819 Nov. 18; Physick, Dr.
    Doctor Horner (?)
  - Letter to Knowles, John, 1819 Dec. 20; Leslie, John
    1969-819ms
  - Letter to Phillips, R., 1820 Feb. 15; Faraday, Michael, 1791-1867
  - Letter to Philadelphia. Mayor, 1820 Mar. 29; Barton, William P. C., (William Paul Crillon), 1786-1856
  - Letter to Vulliamy & Sons, 1820 Apr. 15; Doublas, Marquis of Queensbury
  - Letter to Walker, George, 1820 Aug. 1; Vaughan, John, 1756-1841
    Unlocated June 2011.
  - Letter to Vulliamy, Benjamin Lewis, 1780-1854, 1820 Nov. 12; Bolingbroke, Lord
  - Letter to Unidentified recipient, 1821 Jan. 25; Howley, William, 1766-1848
  - Letter to Unidentified recipient, 1821 Mar. 28; Sabine, Joseph
  - Letter to Unidentified recipient, 1821 Jun. 15; Zach, Franz Xaver, Freiherr von, 1754-1832
  - Letter to McCall, Hugh, 1821 Jul. 7; Bomford, George
  - Letter to Vulliamy, Benjamin Lewis, 1780-1854, 1821 Jul. 18; Peel, Robert, 1788-1850
  - Letter to Bone, Mr., 1821 Oct. 31; Sophie, Princess
  - Letter to Harvey, George, 1821 Dec. 12; Robertson, A.
  - Letter to Harlan, Richard, 1796-1843, 1822 Jan. 2; Audubon, John James, 1785-1851
  - Letter to Silliman, Benjamin, 1779-1864, 1822 Jan. 5; Schoolcraft, Henry Rowe, 1793-1864
    1961-1851ms
  - Letter to Unidentified recipient, 1823 Jan. 1; Wood, J.
    1977-733b.ms
  - Letter to D'Hombres-Firmas, Louis-Augustin, Baron, 1823 Apr. 20; Marmin
  - Letter to Thouin, André, 1747-1824, 1823 Sep. 7; Cuvier, Georges, Baron, 1769-1832
  - Letter to West, William, 1823 Sep. 21; Leslie, John
  - Letter to Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844, 1823 Oct. 20; Macneven, William James, 1763-1841
  - Letter to Laddiges, George, 1823 Nov. 5; Graham, Robert
  - Letter to Vulliamy, Benjamin Lewis, 1780-1854, 1824 Mar. 2; Clinton, Lord
  - Letter to Carey, William, 1824 Apr. 2; Roscoe, William
  - Letter to Vulliamy, Benjamin Lewis, 1780-1854, 1824 Jun. 23; Brunel, Marc Isambard, 1769-1849
  - Letter to La Roy & Bayard, 1824 Sep. 18; Seybert, Adam,1773-1825.
  - Letter to Clarke, 1824 Oct. 29; Fryer, Edward, 1761-1826
  - Letter to Webster, Thomas, 1773-1844, 1825 May 22; Scrope, George Poulette, 1797-1876
    1962-1459ms
  - Letter to Blood, Dr., 1825 Jun. 15; Porter, Augustus S.
  - Letter to Parker, C., 1825 Nov. 28; Beck, Lewis C. (Lewis Caleb), 1798-1853
  - Letter to Unidentified recipient, 1825 Dec. 17; Zach, Franz Xaver, Freiherr von, 1754-1832
  - Phrynium myrosma. Monandria monogynia. [Broadside], 1826 Jan. 19; Roscoe, William
  - Letter to Magrath, E., 1826 Feb. 2; Bowring, John
  - Letter to Unidentified recipient, 1826 Feb. 9; Zach, Franz Xaver, Freiherr von, 1754-1832
  - Letter to Unidentified recipient, 1826 Apr. 30; Zach, Franz Xaver, Freiherr von, 1754-1832
  - Letter to Scott, J. B., 1826 May 12; Gell, William, 1777-1836